{"tossups": [{"question": "This force was tasked with defending the village of Hubbardton as Ebenezer Francis\u2019s main army marched to Castleton. This force included a man who was later charged under the Sedition Act while serving in Congress, Mathew Lyon. John Stark was assisted by this unit at the Battle of Bennington where they were led by Seth Warner. Fort Crown Point was taken by this militia in the leadup to the capture of Fort Ticonderoga. For the point, name this Vermont-based Revolutionary War-era militia led by Ethan Allen.", "answer": "<b> Green Mountain Boys</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "With Knut Fraenkel and Nils Strindberg, Salomon August Andr\u00b4ee attempted to accomplish this feat in a hydrogen balloon called the<em> Eagle</em>. With the help of Lincoln Ellsworth, the first verifiable attempt to do this action took place aboard Umberto Nobile\u2019s airship<em> Norge</em>. Wally Herbert disputed whether the African-American explorer Matthew Henson was the first to accomplish this feat. Credit for accomplishing this feat first was for many years unquestionably given to Robert Peary. For the point, name this feat accomplished in a dirigible in 1926 by Roald Amundsen.", "answer": "Reaching the<b> North Pole</b> (accept equivalent descriptions of<b> North Pole</b> exploration; prompt on \u201cArctic\u201d exploration)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A person who held this political position wrote the book<em> Why Women Should Rule the World</em>. A recent man to hold this position said even Hitler \u201cdidn\u2019t sink to using chemical weapons\u201d and, like his predecessors, did most of his work in a room named for James Brady. That man in this position used what Kellyanne Conway labeled \u201calternative facts\u201d to describe the crowd size at Donald Trump\u2019s inauguration. Sean Spicer, Sarah Huckabee Sanders, and Stephanie Grisham have served in, for the point, what White House position, the spokesperson for the Executive branch?", "answer": "White House<b> Press Secretary</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This event was aided by Fernando Soleti, who ordered the<em> Carabinieri</em> to stand down. The target of this event had earlier been replaced by Pietro Badoglio and transported to the Apennine Mountains. This event was codenamed Operation Oak, and during this event, troops at the Campo Imperatore Hotel were surprised by SS paratroopers arriving on gliders. The target of this event was tracked by Otto Skorzeny and later led the Republic of Sal\u00b4o. For the point, name this 1943 event in which German troops rescued Italian prime minister Benito Mussolini.", "answer": "<b> Gran Sasso raid</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This organization backed the plaintiff in<em> Loewe v. Lawlor</em> which concerned non-corporate application of the Sherman Antitrust Act. This organization called Henry Wallace \u201ca front for the Communist Party,\u201dand it merged with an organization which was defeated in 1946\u2019s \u201cOperation Dixie.\u201d This organization was joined by the United Mine Workers in 1944, led by John L. Lewis. At its founding in 1886, this organization elected its first president, Samul Gompers. For the point, name this union that split from the Knights of Labor and later merged with the CIO.", "answer": "<b> American Federation of Labor</b> (accept<b> AFL</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Author Gianna Braschi\u2019s novel<em> United States of...</em>this good is a postmodern allegory that addresses the colonial status of Puerto Rico and Latin American immigration. A Miguel \u00b4Angel Asturias trilogy tells of how Guatemalan natives were exploited by producers of this good. Mr. Brown owns a company that produces this good in a novel in which Jos\u00b4e Arcadio Segundo is the sole survivor of a massacre of this good\u2019s harvesters. For the point, name this good whose inclusion in<em> One Hundred Years of Solitude</em> was inspired by the United Fruit Company.", "answer": "<b> Banana</b>s", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "This Englishman\u2019s government faced questions after the disappearance of MI6 diver Lionel Crabb on a reconnaissance mission. A \u201cLaw Not War\u201d rally in Trafalgar Square against this leader led by Aneurin Bevan opposed Operation Musketeer. The leader of the \u201cGlamour Boys,\u201d this man resigned his post of Foreign Secretary after the Munich Agreement. Guy Mollet and this man lost their highest offices after a conflict with Gamel Abdel Nasser. For the point, name this British prime minister who resigned after the Suez Crisis.", "answer": "Anthony<b> Eden</b>, 1st Earl of Avon (<b>1</b>st Earl of<b> Avon</b>, accept Viscount<b> Eden</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This country was united against European rule by the Yaruba Dynasty. Iran and the Soviet Union backed opposing sides in this country during the Dhofar Rebellion. This country\u2019s final elected Imam, Ghalib Alhinai, fled to Saudi Arabia in 1959 after the Jebel Akhdar War. This country\u2019s Kumzari-speaking population has typically been based in Musandam. At its 19th century peak, this country\u2019s influence reached from the Strait of Hormuz to the coast of central Africa. For the point, name this country, whose royal ruling house since 1744 has been the House of Al Said.", "answer": "Sultanate of<b> Oman</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A seated bronze statue of this man, whose left shoe is rubbed by tourists and students for luck, was created in 1884 by Daniel Chester French and place in a \u201cYard\u201d named for this man. This man donated 400 volumes and over 700 pounds to the creation of a school that briefly moved to Concord during the American Revolution. That school named for this man was the site of a clerical dispute that resulted in the creation of a rival institution in New Haven. For the point, name this man whose gifts helped found the oldest university in the United States.", "answer": "<b> John Harvard</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man returned to Italy with a large Hunnic force at the command of the usurper Joannes and later obtained the rank of Magister Militum per Gallias from Joannes\u2019s successor. This man defeated his rival Bonifacius at the Battle of Rimini, but he was later assassinated by his own Emperor Valentinian III. Another of this man\u2019s victories came at a battle where his forces, alongside a Visigothic army commanded by King Theodoric, defeated the army of Attila the Hun, the Battle of the Catalaunian Plains. For the point, name this man, often called the \u201cLast of the Romans\u2019.", "answer": "Flavius<b> Aetius</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The conquest of this region was begun after the Battle of Chuvash Cape. Forts built in this region were known as<em> ostrog</em> and were used to house participants in the<em> katorga</em> labor system. The border of this region was defined with its southern neighbor by the Treaty of Nerchinsk. After the conquest of Kazan, the exploration of this region was begun by the<em> ataman</em> Yermak and financed by the Stroganov family. Early attempts to build transportation across this region included the Irkutsk-Chita Project. For the point, name this vast eastern region of Russia.", "answer": "<b> Siberia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In the leadup to this period, 16 prisoners were executed in Rawson Prison in the Trelew Massacre. During this period, masked men abducted people like Emilce Moler and Pablo D\u00b4\u0131az in the \u201cNight of the Pencils.\u201d The Nobel Peace Prize was awarded to Adolfo P\u00b4erez Esquivel for his opposition to actions such as the \u201cdisappearing\u201d of \u201clos desaparacidos\u201d under Jorge Rafael Videla during this period. The Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo held up pictures of their abducted children during, for the point, what troubled period from 1976 to 1983 in Argentina?", "answer": "<b> Dirty War</b> (accept La<b> guerra sucia</b>, prompt on \u201cOperation Condor\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This figure\u2019s existence was questioned by Bruno Bauer based on the influence of Stoic philosophy, a thesis shared by Arthur Drews in a 1909 book. Ernest Renan claimed that in the absence of this figure, Mithras would have been the most widely worshipped god in the Mediterranean. Albert Schweitzer claimed that this figure was an \u201capocalypticist\u201d in a book titled<em> The Quest for the Historical</em> this figure. The earliest historical references to this figure include Josephus and Tacitus. For the point, name this ancient rabbi whose life is attested to by the Gospels.", "answer": "<b> Jesus Christ</b> (accept either underlined portion)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The<em> Ancien R\u00b4egime</em> was ended during, for the point, the reign of this king who was executed during the French Revolution.", "answer": "<b> Louis XVI</b> of France", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Chester A. Arthur defended African-American schoolteacher Elizabeth Jennings Graham in a case that desegregated these systems in Manhattan. Andrew Smith Hallidie promoted one of these systems named for Clay Street Hill. Charles Tyson Yerkes was a \u201ctraction magnate\u201d of one of these systems on Chicago\u2019s North Side. These vehicles traveled down the Desire line in the French Quarter of New Orleans, which inspired a Tennessee Williams play. For the point, name this form of public transit exemplified by San Francisco\u2019s cable cars.", "answer": "<b> Streetcar</b>s (accept<b> trolley</b>s,<b> tram</b>s,<b> tramcar</b>s, or<b> electric rail</b>ways) Page 6", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A work painted during this war and displayed in the Philadelphia Museum of Art depicts a brown wooden box below a monster whose arms and legs awkwardly hold one another. This war inspired both <em>Soft Construction with Boiled Beans</em> and a work that was covered by a curtain during a Colin Powell presentation to the United Nations. A horse with a knife for its tongue, a woman with her dead child, and a bull representing fascism all appear in a work inspired by this war. For the point, name this conflict that inspired Pablo Picasso\u2019s<em> Guernica</em>.", "answer": "<b> Spanish Civil</b> War (accept Guerra<b> Civil Espa\u02dcnola</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This leader ordered an attack on the Golden Temple as part of Operation Blue Star. This leader was on the way to an interview with Peter Ustinov when she was killed by two Sikh militants in 1984, leaving her son Rajiv in power. For the point, name this woman, the first and only female prime minister of India.", "answer": "<b> I</b>ndira<b> Gandhi</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The rulers of this city of antiquity moved from the Great Palace to the Palace of Blachernae in the 11th century. Some foreign merchants in this city lived in the Galata quarter. A famed column moved to this city from Delphi is made up of three intertwined snakes and stands next to an obelisk built by Thutmose III. This city\u2019s harbor was defended by a long chain and is known as the Golden Horn. Once defended by the Theodosian Walls, this city was conquered by Mehmed II in 1453. For the point, name this city, the capital of the Byzantine Empire.", "answer": "<b> Constantinople</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This service required employees to pledge to refrain from using profane language or drinking alcohol. An advertisement for employees for this service asked for young fellows \u201cwilling to risk death daily,\u201dnoting \u201cOrphans preferred.\u201d This service was founded by the trio of Russell, Majors, and Waddell and began operations in April 1860, when a man who may be Johnson William Richardson left St. Joseph with objects that arrived in Sacramento ten days later. The transcontinental telegraph rendered obsolete, for the point, what mail service that utilized riders and horses?", "answer": "<b> Pony Express</b> Page 7", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Police officers arrested conspirators in a broken down elevator in this country\u2019s Municipal Library Elevator Coup. In 1910, Manuel Bu\u00b4\u0131\u00b8ca of the Carbon\u00b4aria killed the king of this country and his first born son, Lu\u00b4\u0131s Felipe. This country\u2019s African empire was represented on the Pink Map, which led to an 1890 British Ultimatum. This country\u2019s Second Republic ended in 1974 when a coup overthrew Marcello Caetano. For the point, name this country whose Third Republic came to power after the Carnation Revolution.", "answer": "<b> Portugal</b> (accept<b> Portuguese Republic</b>) Page 8", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}